So, this is Blender. It can do 3D
modeling, texturing, lighting, shading,
and rendering. And I'm going to show you
how to do all of those things whilst you
make your very own doughut. And I know
this looks complex and challenging, but
I promise you it is achievable for even
a complete beginner that has never
opened Blender such as yourself. And I
know this because millions of beginners
have already made their doughnut because
this is the fifth version of this
tutorial. I remake it for every major
Blender release. This one for Blender
5.0. And speaking of which, if you have
already made a donut from a previous
version, rather than make another one,
I've actually just released a course
designed for postdonut beginners. So, if
you're interested in that, you can click
the link below. For everybody else, you
need to download Blender. So, if you
haven't already, click the link below.
That'll take you to blender.org and then
just hit the big download button. Now,
if you're on Windows, that'll download
an executable, which you should install.
If you're on a Mac, it's an application
you drag to your applications folder.
And also, if you're at school or you're
on a work computer that won't let you
install anything, you can still use
Blender. If you download the portable
zip version of Blender, then just unzip
it. You can run Blender from the folder.
Pretty cool. Anyway, however you got
Blender, open it, and you should see
this. Then just click anywhere off the
splash screen to close it. And you're in
Blender. Hey, welcome. So this big
section, this big gray area here, this
is your 3D viewport. And it's where
you'll spend probably 98% of your time
because it's the it's the 3D world.
Whether you're making a character,
you're building an environment, it all
happens right here. Um, so the first
thing you need to learn is how to move
around in this space. And you can orbit
by middle mouse pushing. So your scroll
wheel, if you just push it in until it
clicks, that's your middle mouse button.
And then if you just drag that around,
you can orbit. If you don't have a
middle mouse button, a lot of people
don't. They're on like a laptop with a
trackpad or something. You guys will
struggle. It's definitely easier if you
have a mouse. Uh but in a pinch, top
right hand corner, you just mouse over
this little circle and then just click
and drag on that. Um that'll do the same
thing. Or the third alternative way to
do it, edit preferences and then
underneath input emulate threeb button
mouse and then if you hold down alt and
then leftclick drag um that will do the
same thing. I don't want that. By the
way, whilst I am here, a value that you
will want to change if you're on a 4K
monitor, you will probably have noticed
that like Blender looks like this where
like everything is really super tiny and
you have to squint to see it. So,
underneath interface, I change my
resolution scale to at least a 1.5. Um,
usually like 1.8. Um, but for tutorials,
I go even higher so you can really see
everything, but it's obviously much
easier to use when you can see things
clearly. Okay, so middle mouse drag,
that's how you orbit around. You can see
we're focusing on our cube at the
moment, though. So, how do we move to
somewhere else? You do that by shift
middle mouse drag, and that will pan you
somewhere else. You can also over here
on the the side there, click that little
hand. That will do the same thing. But
yeah, shift middle mouse drag or middle
mouse drag to orbit. And what about
zoom? You can probably guess, you might
have already done it by mistake, but
just zooming by scrolling in and out on
your wheel. Or again, you can go to the
little magnifying glass there. Just
click on that and do that. Or
alternatively, control middle mouse and
then that will also move you in as well.
So, I've thrown a lot of keyboard
shortcuts at you already. Middle mouse
for this, shift, middle mouse to pan,
um, scroll. If you don't want to have to
remember all the hotkeys, cuz I'm going
to throw a lot more at you. If you don't
want to have to write them down
yourself, I have done it for you. So, I
put together a Google doc with all of
the most common hotkeys and short key
shortcuts that you might need to use.
Um, and it's free. So, just click the
link below and you can, um, print it
out, you can stick it on your wall. Um,
a lot of people do that and it's u big
time saver. Okay, now it's really common
to like get lost like one way is to like
end up upside down like this and then
you're like which way is up? How do I,
you know, if you just over here these
little um these little this gizmo thing,
these these colored circle things with
lines, those are your axes. So if you
just click on one of those, that'll
reorient yourself. So the Z, that's the
top axis. And then you just you're back,
right? you know which way is up because
it's it's it's that way, right? Which
way that one is pointing. Another way,
like if you got like really off into the
weeds, like you were over here, and then
you're like, "How do I how do I get back
to where I was?" Um, if you've got an
object selected and you just want to
focus on like just fly to it, um, and
this is a really common hotkey. You use
it all the time. Uh, it's numpad period,
and that'll just fly you to that. If you
don't have a numpad, like even a lot of
keyboards today, they don't sell them
with numpads anymore, I guess, cuz
people aren't accountants. They don't
need to quickly type in numbers. But I
love them cuz it's really useful for
Blender. Um, if you don't have one,
[laughter] um, you can also use the
tilda key, which is that little key
underneath your escape key. So, if you
hold that down and then just drag over
where it says view selected and then
release, that'll do the exact same
thing. So, that is how you can quickly
change focus to the selected object. Um,
and yeah, as I said, you do this all the
time. Um, but yeah, I'm going to be
using numpad period from now on. Okay,
so we're making a donut. We do not need
our cube here. So, let's delete it. You
can just hit delete on your keyboard.
Um, or what I like to do is hit X, which
is the alternative way. And, um, it's
just easier cuz my finger is like right
there. I know it's another hotkey to
remember, but you delete stuff a lot as
well, and it's helpful to not have to
find that key. So, X, and then delete.
And now I want to add a new object. And
I can do that by going to add at the top
of the screen there. Or alternatively,
the hotkey, another one to throw at you,
shift A, and that'll just put it
wherever your cursor is. And it's the
exact same list. But this list here is,
I mean, it's extensive. There's stuff in
here that I have never used in my 21
years of using Blender. speaker. Never
ever used it. Don't know what it's for.
Um, most of the time what you're looking
for is underneath mesh. So, these are
your primitive mesh objects. And
generally, when you're making something,
you pick one of these that most
resembles or is closest to what it is
you're making. Like, if you're making a
mailbox, you might start with a cube.
You're making a a lamp post, you might
start with a cylinder. We're starting.
Well, we're trying to make a donut. So,
we need to start with a Taurus, which is
basically a donut. Look at that. So,
that's cool. It's a wimpy looking donut
though, right? It's very, very flimsy.
We want to make it look uh more thicker,
right? So, in the bottom left hand
corner, there's a little box that says
add Taurus. And this has additional
options for us. Now, if you accidentally
clicked off after you added the Taurus,
that box is gone. Um, you can
momentarily bring it back by hitting F9,
but that's only if you haven't changed
something. So, essentially, yeah, it
it's called the last used function in
Blender. So, immediately after you do an
action in Blender, sometimes you see in
the bottom lefthand corner additional
options which you can tweak and change
things if you need. So, if you don't see
it, it just means you've done something
else and it's gone. Um, but yeah, you
can bring it back uh momentarily by
hitting F9 sometimes, but I usually just
like redo it. Um, anyways, so first
thing I want to change is uh the size of
this thing. So, it is 1 m, which is like
3 ft for the Americans. It's a big
donut. Um, probably shouldn't be that
big. It should be about 10% of that. So,
0.1, which is 10 cm, roughly about that.
And then if I zoom in by scrolling
forward, I just need to change my minor
radius until it looks somewhat like a
donut. So I want to just uh orbit up
right and around. So I'm just middle
mouse moving so I can see the inside.
Then I'll just scroll in like so until
Yeah. And I'm just going to change this
value until it looks like uh like a
donut. Now you can see as I move this
like it's going really quick and I can't
get it on the right value. So, when
you're clicking and dragging on a value
in Blender, if you hold down shift, that
will use smaller increments.
[clears throat]
Um, and that's another one you use all
the time. Um, because it's, uh, yeah,
sometimes you need small values and it's
helpful to get smaller increments like
that. So, that's pretty good. I might go
with that. Yeah, about a 057.
Okay. And then the other thing you can
change here is like the resolution of
the donut. Um, you know, you can go like
really PlayStation one graphics maybe.
Um, I'm going to keep it at 48, but I'm
going to increase the other one to about
Yeah, let's go 18 like that. Um,
16, 18. Yeah, we'll go 18. Um, and
that's just a little bit more
resolution, and it's just going to help
us a little bit later on when we start
to shape um the donut. Okay. But once
I've got that, I can just click off. And
now those options are gone. We've
committed. That's it. That is the
starting point of our donut. Now, the
next thing you're probably wondering is
it still kind of looks like PlayStation
One graphics, Andrew. Um, and that's
because it has flat shading. So,
basically, there's two states for a
mesh. Um, there's smooth shading or
there is flat shading, and it defaults
to flat. If you want to change it to
smooth, you just rightclick the object
and then go shade smooth like that. And
there we go. It's fixed. So it basically
shades smooth without getting too
technical. Anytime there is like two
faces, it just kind of smooths out that
point like fakery. So it's not actually
adding any additional computation times
which is important. Um but it's
appearing to the eye to be smooth. Okay.
So um in previous doughnut versions we
would uh start making the icing. And
although that's fun to make like
dribbling icing, um it can be a little
complicated. a lot of users uh ran into
their first uh roadblocks at that that
time. So instead, we're going to do
something a little bit easier to start
with um and more practical, and that's
to make a coffee mug. So, we need to add
in a new object, which if you can
remember from before, it's the add menu
at the top there, or the hotkey as I
like to use, shift A. And then
underneath mesh, you're looking for
something that most resembles the object
you're trying to create. No prizes for
guessing, the cylinder. Okay. So, it
comes in very very big. It's uh
completely engulfing our donut. So,
again, in the bottom lefthand corner. Uh
click that little add cylinder. And then
I'm going to change the radius first of
all just to bring this back. You can
like do this after the fact like resize
something. Um but it just helps to, you
know, at this point see it all together.
Um I think I'm going to make it around
holding down shift and just kind of drag
it back and forth. Yeah, about.13
or exactly.13.
Uh and then the depth. This is just the
height of it. And again, you can change
this later on, but just want to see it
roughly the right size. The big one
that's important is the vertices. And
we're actually going to make this look
more low res. Now, why would we make it
look more low res? Um cuz now it's
obviously very jagged. The reason for
this is that very soon we're going to be
adding in something called a subsurf
modifier, which adds over the top of our
existing mesh. it adds more geometry
like it doubles the geometry and it kind
of smooths it out. So actually if you
start too high like this then you're
adding like doubling that geometry and
doubling it again and then you can
quickly end up with something that's too
computationally heavy. So when you're
working and you know you're going to be
doing something subdiv sometimes it
helps to start like chunkier low res. Um
anyway just just trust me and set it to
uh 14 like that. Okay great. So, we've
got another object and they are
completely overlapping. So, how do we
separate things? Um, some of you might
already know this. You can guess right
left hand side there, there's a tool
that looks like it would be able to move
something. It's the move tool. So, this
is one way to move things. You activate
that and you get this little gizmo. And
look, I can move it and I can separate
them. Um, so this is moving things along
the axes. Um, you can also uh just drag
on that uh click and drag on that little
white circle there. And then that's like
freehand uh drag around. I will say most
Blender users don't actually use and
move things this way because it's a lot
of effort every time you want to move
something to like go to the sidebar,
activate the tool, you know, click it,
move it. It's like most people don't do
that. Instead, they remember the hotkey
and the hotkey to move in Blender. And
you'll be using this a lot. So again,
this is on my keyboard shortcut. Um,
it's it's all in there. But the hotkey
is G. G for grab. Now, you will notice
very quickly that when you tap G, the
moment you tap it, you are already in
the move state. So, it's now attached to
my cursor even though I didn't click.
Okay. So, and here's the other thing. My
cursor could be on the other side of the
screen. Doesn't have to be anywhere near
the object. And then the moment you tap
G, it's now anchored to that cursor. Um,
and even more I I think it's cool when
you go to the other side of the screen,
it actually your cursor appears on the
other side. So it's just like an
infinitely repeating um thing there.
[clears throat] But at first this is
like hard to wrap your head around
because Blender does this for a lot of
things like not just moving something
but also rotating something. The moment
I tap R, which is how to rotate
something, or S. Okay, that's I thought
I might as well just teach you all three
at the same time. So, G to move
something, G for grab, R to rotate, or S
to scale something. But you'll see in
each of those states, the moment you hit
the key, no matter where your cursor is,
it's uh it's in that state. And that's
actually a good thing because as I said,
the number of times you need to move
things and rotate and scale things in
3D, if you had to every single time
change the tool, then move your cursor
over to it, click it, activate it,
that's a lot of extra steps. So, it's
actually really cool to have this like
just one tap key and it's already
activated. Um, [clears throat] anyways.
Okay. So, but uh whilst I'm in uh the
move state by tapping G, um I can also
uh lock it to a specific axis just like
um with with those arrows that you saw
before. So, just when it's in that move
state, you tap the the axis you want to
move it on. So, that's the X axis. The Y
brings it back and forwards and the Z is
um up and down. Okay. And that's
correct. Blender is Z up, Y backwards
and forwards. Different 3D applications
have different things. There's no like
standard. But yeah, that's how Blenders
is. And by the way, if you forget which
letter is which axis, you can actually
see them up there in that little circle
there. So again, X, Y, and uh and Z.
Anyways, I want to move this actually
just a little bit further back right
there. So I want my my donut to be the
uh front and center, and I want this to
be at the back there. But then, how do I
change my view? So I'm no longer just
pivoting on my donut. I want to shift my
focus to that selected object. It's
number pad period or again holding down
that tilda key under your escape button
and then hitting uh view selected is the
same thing. Okay. So let's make this
look like a coffee mug. So we have to
edit this object. And uh to edit an
object we have to change what mode we
are in. So in the top leftand corner of
the screen there's a little drop down
which if you click we can change it into
edit mode. Okay. So when you're in edit
mode you can see the state has changed.
The object that was selected now has a
bunch of points and lines on it. Um and
you'll also notice whilst you're in edit
mode, you can't actually select any
object. And it's it's worth pointing out
this because this is a really common
thing. A lot of beginners, they they
say, "I I don't know what happened, but
I couldn't select anything in Blender."
And usually it's just they're in the
wrong state. They're in edit mode. They
forgot. And then they tried to like come
over here and then click something and
they're like, "Why is it not selecting?"
Okay, so you have to be in object mode
if you want to select an object. And if
you want to edit something, you have to
be in edit mode. Um, but going to this
dropown and doing this time and again
would uh again be annoying. So, Blender,
of course, has a hotkey for it, and that
is tab. So, tab will just cycle you in
and out of object and edit mode, just
those two states. Um, which is great
because you need to use this all the
time. So, you usually come in, do some
editing, uh, go back into object mode,
select something else, edit that one, go
back to this. Um, so that's, uh, yeah,
good one to remember. Tab. All right.
So, in edit mode, when I'm in this state
here, these little points here, these
are called vertices. These are the
points that make up the um yeah, the
shape of the mesh, obviously. Um and
then you've got um edges. And uh you can
actually select um by changing the
selection type from vertices, which is
the default, to edges, clicking that
little button. And then I can click on
the edges or select faces. Okay? Like
this. And again, Blender has hotkeys for
everything. So, if you want to just know
the hotkey, it's one to do verticy
select, two to do edge select, and then
three to do face select. Again, make
sure you get my keyboard shortcut
shortcut guide cuz it's uh it's a lot to
remember. So, I want to select the top
of this uh cup here. It's got a lid on
it that I don't want. So, se in face
select mode. Selecting that face, I'm
going to hit X. Now, it's going to ask
me what part do you want to delete? Um,
which might sound redundant, but there
is quite a lot of times in Blender you
want to delete, even though you've
selected a bunch of faces, you want to
delete the entire vertices of those
faces. So, we have to confirm. We want
to delete just the faces from this list.
And there we go. So, we've now got a cup
with a hole in it. Great. But this cup
will not do. It is too paper thin. We
could cut our finger on that edge there.
So, we need to add some thickness to
this cup. And while we could do this in
edit mode, like you could select
everything and extrude it in and
whatnot, um, we don't need to because
there is actually a function we can do
to add thickness to anything without
needing to go into edit mode. And that
is underneath your modifier stack here.
So, if you click this little wrench,
this little activate modifiers. Let's
just drag this out. And if you click add
modifier at the top there, you can see
you've got a number of different
options. Um, and the one that we're
looking for is solidify. So, this is
underneath the generate and just in case
this changes for a future version of
Blender, you can also go to search at
the top there and you could just type in
um solidify from the list. Okay, so now
now that we've got that, you can see
we've got a bunch of options and you'll
notice that our mesh now has some
thickness to it. And I can change this
thickness here. Now watch what happens
as I enter into edit mode. You will
notice as I select these faces here, I
can't select this thick this inside part
of the uh of the cup there. And that's
an important point because modifiers are
not actually adjusting the real mesh. So
the real mesh still exists here. Um if I
disable this from the viewport by
clicking this little um monitor button
there, you'll see that my mesh has not
changed. This is just applying this
effect after the fact. So, it's
basically in object mode. It's taking
whatever mesh that you give it, which is
this, and then it's adding thickness to
every face essentially. Um, so the
reason this is um so useful is that this
is a non-destructive workflow. So, I
could at any point I could be doing a
bunch of changes to my my mug here. I
could, you know, we'll get to all that
later on. We could change the size and
things and then later on I can go m you
know what, I don't I think that's a
little bit too thick. I'm going to
change that and I can come back to that
and very quickly um adjust it. So
non-destructive and it's obviously very
helpful um for a lot of things. [snorts]
Okay. So I've given it some thickness,
but I also want to round um this corner
here. That's way too jagged. Just like
before I said I we want to um we're
going to add in an extra layer on top
which adds more geometry. And that is
called your uh add modify generate
subdivision surface. So yeah, all the
way down there. You use it all the time,
but it's like buried in there. Okay, so
subdivision surface. So this appears to
have like screwed up the mesh. It's
like, wo, what actually happened there?
Let's just increase the uh levels
viewport. So this is just increasing the
number of times that it um doubles the
geometry.
So you can see this is what we start
with, right? This is the the start. This
is one level. Then this is two levels.
And then this is three levels. And every
time you do it, it's doubling the
geometry. Um, and but you can see it's
giving us the effect we want. It's
smoothing out that edge there. But
because of the way that it works, like
basically if you look at uh let's go
back to this. Um, we've got this this
hard corner here, right? It's just like
a 90° corner. So let me get in a little
bit closer here so you can kind of see
it. Um, yeah, it's like a 90° perfectly
like that. So, when you add in a
subdivision surface, it's basically
saying, okay, so there's a point here,
there is a point all the way over here,
and there is a point that's going to go
all like it's it's so far it's off the
screen, but it's all the way down there.
So, what I need to do is I need to
average out those points. So, take the
middle point of those three. So,
essentially from here to
somewhere around here. And I'm going to
add in a point like here, right? And
then if you do another level, like level
two, it then places a point here. And
then another point here. And then if you
do another level, it places another
point here, another point here, another
point here. And because there's two
sides to this um uh mug, there's like
another one happening on that side,
right? So we've now just got this like
really super like ovalshaped edge like
this. Okay? Which is why when I turn it
on, we get this effect there. So what we
first of all need to do in edit mode
with our uh mug here. Um so I am in I
doesn't matter what mode I'm actually in
here. Um but what I need to do is
essentially tighten an edge where that
that uh that smoothing is happening. So
it's no longer happening from all the
way here to smooth it all the way down
to there. I want to happen it like just
to about there. So I need to add in more
geometry onto this mesh here. So to do
that uh we need to add a loop cut. That
is how you add in another level of uh
another edge. So ct controllr will add
in this loop cut. I believe you can also
find it from the mesh
like somewhere in here. [clears throat]
Yeah, there you go. Uh edge loop cut and
slide if you wanted to look it in there.
But it's yeahr. That's another one you
use all the time.
>> [snorts]
>> So, when I'm in when I hit CtrlR, it's
it's saying where do you want to place
the cut in this mesh? Um, and I could
place it, you know, anywhere anywhere
between uh a face essentially. So, I'm
going to place it along this middle. So,
you do a single click and then it's
saying where do you want to place that
vertically on this uh th this this row
of of faces essentially. Um, so you can
see as I bring it towards the top there,
it's tightening that edge there. Okay.
And that's exactly what I want. I want
that edge to be much tighter than it was
um before. Um so that edge is now
looking good. But now what about this
one at the bottom there? This one's
looking even worse. We got a lot to fix
here. Um but first I need to do another
loop cut. So CtrlR and then again single
click to confirm I want it on that that
uh row of faces. And then I'm just
sliding it along until it's you know
roughly about there at the bottom of my
mug. Okay. And then you can see it's
like this whole area here, this this
face here, it's become like a like it's
turned it into a star. And not to get
too complicated, but basically a subsurf
modifier, it has to has to know what to
do. And generally, if there's like faces
that are made up of four vertices, this
is getting complicated. I can tell it
knows what to do. It makes it like nice
and smooth. But the moment you have a
face that is made up of more than four
vertices, it's called an engon. and it
doesn't really know what to do with it.
I mean, it does, but you don't know what
it's going to do. Um, and it just can
make things look a little ugly. Endone
is kind of like a dirty word in in 3D
space. It's like, h, you never want to
have an engon. They are actually useful
and they, you know, do have a purpose,
but generally generally speaking,
they're good to uh avoid if you don't
know what you're doing. So, anyway, I
should tell you what I'm doing. The the
way to fix this is I need to add another
loop that kind of just goes around here,
right? that. So that way I've only got
from there to there and then I can have
my ugly star or whatever happening
underneath my coffee mug. So I need to
uh add a loop cut, but I can't add a
loop cut on just a single face. Instead,
what I need to do is um it's called
inset to take a single face and then
just like add in a loop around that
face. And you do that by hitting I. So I
and then just like it's already active.
Again, this is the the way why I spent a
while to explain it. The moment you
activate a tool, you're already in that
selection state. So, I hit I and
wherever my cursor is, it's now going
like, where do you want to put this
inset? Okay. So, I'm just moving it back
and forth until I get it. You know, how
tight do I want this edge to look?
Something like
that, maybe. I mean, it's it's
underneath the coffee mug. doesn't
really matter that much, but um yeah,
something something like that. And there
we go. So, you can see this looks a lot
nicer. [snorts] And again, because we
are in a non-destructive workflow, I've
still got my solidify modifier at the
top here, right? I could change the
thickness of this. I can make this a
really chunky looking coffee mug or a
really thin one. Um and that is the
benefit of a non-destructive workflow.
And then I can also change how how high-
res do I want my coffee mug to look. Um,
and this is the way to work in 3D. This
is the best way to do it because, you
know, if a client wants you to change
something or whatnot, keeping in a
flexible um workflow is uh definitely a
good place to be. Okay, so we have
created the start of a coffee mug and we
have also created um a donut. Good time
to save. Good time to save. So, file,
save as, or shift controls and then save
as.
So, the way I like to save things, and
you might want to copy this, is to um
you come up with a name, you know,
underscore, whatever. Um, and then you
put a number after it, and then you can
actually see I've already saved my file.
Um, I don't want to override my existing
save in case I need to go back to it for
whatever reason. So, I just want to add
a number to it. And in other softwares,
you know, you have to come here and you
have to type in the number, right? Not
Blender. Blender has a hotkey for
everything. If you hit plus or minus on
your numpad or on the little uh field
here, oh, you can't even see it. I'm
right over the top of it right there.
This little field, these little plus and
minus, it'll automatically add a number
to the end of your um file. Um so that's
yeah, really useful. So, I'm just going
to add uh a two there, and I'm going to
hit save. All right. So, if you're
watching this in the split version of
the tutorial, um you can click here to
watch part two. Or if you're watching
the combined single long video at the
end, you can just keep on watching. BC
go.